♪ ♪
♪ I should’ve known ♪
♪ I’d leave alone ♪
♪ Just goes to show ♪
♪ That the blood you bleed
Is just the blood you owe ♪
♪ We were a pair ♪
♪ ♪
♪ But I saw you there ♪
♪ Too much to bear ♪
♪ You were my life,
But life is far away from fair ♪
♪ Was I stupid to love you ♪
♪ Was I reckless to help ♪
♪ Was it obvious to everybody else ♪
♪ That I’d fallen for a lie ♪
♪ You were never on my side ♪
♪ Fool me once, fool me twice ♪
♪ Are you death or paradise ♪
♪ Now you’ll never see me cry ♪
♪ There’s just no time to die ♪
♪ ♪
♪ I let it burn ♪
♪ You’re no longer my concern ♪
♪ Faces from my past return ♪
♪ Another lesson yet... to learn ♪
♪ That I’d fallen for a lie ♪
♪ You were never on my side ♪
♪ Fool me once, fool me twice ♪
♪ Are you death or paradise ♪
♪ Now you’ll never see me cry ♪
♪ There’s just no time to die ♪
♪ ♪
♪ No time to die ♪
♪ Ooh, ooh ooh ♪
♪ Ooh ♪
♪ Fool me once, fool me twice ♪
♪ Are you death or paradise ♪
♪ Now you’ll never see me cry ♪
♪ There’s just no time to die ♪
♪ ♪