♪♪♪
(♪ MUSIC FADES OUT ♪)
LISTEN UP EVERYBODY.
TONY, BILLY BOY'S BEEN IN PRISON
FOR TWENTY-FIVE YEARS.
HE'S ONLY BEEN OUT
FOR THREE DAYS.
THE LAST TIME YOU
WERE A FREE MAN
THE BROOKLYN DODGERS WERE
STILL THE BROOKLYN DODGERS,
AND EISENHOWER
WAS YOUR PRESIDENT.
LAURA...
(♪ MUSIC STARTS ♪)
AMANDA'S INTRIGUED
WITH BILLY BOY.
BILLY BOY, ASK
AMANDA FOR A DATE.
WE COULD GO TO THE
PARAMOUNT, MAYBE?
AMANDA: THERE IS NO MORE
BROOKLYN PARAMOUNT.
IT'S BEEN TAKEN OVER
BY SOME COLLEGE.
BILLY BOY: OR THE ALBY?
(♪ MUSIC STARTS ♪)
- THAT'S GONE TOO.
YOURE A REGULAR RIP VAN WINKLE,
AREN'T YOU?
♪ I'VE BEEN ALONE WITH YOU ♪
- WHAT HAVE YOU BEEN DOING
THE PAST TWENTY YEARS?
♪ INSIDE MY MIND ♪
BILLY BOY: TWENTY YEARS.
IT'S HARD TO EXPLAIN.
AMANDA: I CAN'T BELIEVE IT.
♪ AND IN MY DREAMS
I'VE KISSED YOUR LIPS ♪
♪ A THOUSAND TIMES ♪
- IT'S BEEN A LONG TIME
SINCE I'VE BEEN ON A DATE.
♪ I SOMETIMES SEE YOU ♪
♪ PASS OUTSIDE MY DOOR ♪
♪ HELLO! ♪
♪ IS IT ME YOU'RE LOOKING FOR? ♪
♪ I CAN SEE IT IN YOUR EYES ♪
♪ I CAN SEE IT IN YOUR SMILE ♪
♪ YOU'RE ALL I'VE EVER WANTED ♪
♪ AND MY ARMS ARE OPEN WIDE ♪
♪ 'CAUSE YOU KNOW
JUST WHAT TO SAY ♪
♪ AND YOU KNOW
JUST WHAT TO DO ♪
♪ AND I WANT TO
TELL YOU SO MUCH ♪
♪ I LOVE YOU ♪
- IT'S OK.
♪ I LONG TO SEE THE
SUNLIGHT IN YOUR HAIR ♪
FRIENDS: HI LAURA,
SORRY WE'RE LATE.
♪ AND TELL YOU TIME
AND TIME AGAIN ♪
♪ HOW MUCH I CARE ♪
♪ SOMETIMES I FEEL MY
HEART WILL OVERFLOW ♪
♪ HELLO! ♪
♪ I'VE JUST GOT TO
LET YOU KNOW ♪
♪ 'CAUSE I WONDER
WHERE YOU ARE ♪
♪ AND I WONDER WHAT YOU DO ♪
♪ ARE YOU SOMEWHERE
FEELING LONELY? ♪
♪ OR IS SOMEONE LOVING YOU? ♪
♪ TELL ME HOW TO
WIN YOUR HEART ♪
♪ FOR I HAVEN'T GOT A CLUE ♪
♪ BUT LET ME START BY SAYING ♪
AMANDA: IT ISN'T GOOD FOR YOU
BILLY BOY.
TOO MANY MEMORIES,
TOO MANY GHOSTS
♪ I LOVE YOU ♪
BILLY BOY: IT'S WHAT I
KNOW. THIS, AND THE CAN.
AMANDA: WE COULD GO TO FLORIDA.
OR WE COULD GO OUT WEST.
BILLY BOY: WHAT ARE YOU TELLING
ME? WHEN DID THIS BECOME...
♪♪♪
(PHONE RINGS)
- HELLO?
♪ HELLO! ♪
♪ IS IT ME YOU'RE
LOOKING FOR? ♪
♪ 'CAUSE I WONDER
WHERE YOU ARE ♪
♪ AND I WONDER WHAT YOU DO ♪
♪ ARE YOU SOMEWHERE
FEELING LONELY? ♪
♪ OR IS SOMEONE LOVING YOU? ♪
♪ TELL ME HOW TO
WIN YOUR HEART ♪
♪ FOR I HAVEN'T GOT A CLUE ♪
♪ BUT LET ME
START BY SAYING ♪
♪ I LOVE YOU ♪
- MR. REYNOLDS.
EXCUSE ME, BUT,
THERE'S SOMETHING GOING
ON IN THE SCULPTURE CLASS.
I THINK YOU OUGHT
TO CHECK IT OUT.
(MUSIC ENDS)
- I'VE WANTED YOU TO
SEE IT SO MANY TIMES.
BUT I FINALLY THINK IT'S DONE.
♪ (BRIDGE MUSIC STARTS AGAIN) ♪
TELL ME WHAT YOU THINK OF IT.
- OH IT'S WONDERFUL.
- THIS IS HOW I SEE YOU.
♪♪♪
♪ HELLO! ♪
♪ IS IT ME YOU'RE LOOKING FOR? ♪
(MUSIC FADES OUT)