In sleep he sang to me
In dreams he came
That voice which calls to me
And speaks my name
And do I dream again
For now I find
The Phantom of the Opera is here
Inside my mind
Sing once again with me
Our strange duet
My power over you
Grows stronger yet
And though you turn from me
To glance behind
The Phantom of the Opera is there
Inside your mind
Those who have seen your face
Draw back in fear
I am the mask you wear
It's me they hear
My spirit and my voice in one combined
The Phantom of the Opera is there
Inside your mind
In all your fantasies
You always knew
That man and mystery
Were both in you
And in this labyrinth
Where night is blind
The Phantom of the Opera is there
Inside my mind
Sing, my angel
He's there the Phantom of The Opera
Aah
Sing my angel of music
Sing my angel
Aah
Sing
Sing to me
Aah